Wendell H. Camp Papers 2006.0173
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Wendell H. Camp Papers
undated, 1933-1954.
2006.0173
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
1.5 Linear feet
The collection contains manuscripts of articles, book chapters, photographs and negatives collected or authored by Dr. Camp for his research. Dr. Camp was a Professor of Botany and Chair of the Botany Department at the University of Connecticut from 1953 until his death in 1963.
Camp, Wendell H.
Biography
Wendell H. Camp, born on February 22, 1904, in Dayton, Ohio, was a Professor of Botany and Head of the Botany Department at the University of Connecticut from 1953-1963. Camp earned his Bachelor of Science at Otterbein College in 1925 and his Master of Science in 1926 as well as his Ph.D.in 1932 from Ohio University. Camp began his teaching career during his sophmore and junior years at Otterbein College where he was an assistant in Botany. During his senior year, Camp became an instructor of Geology. At Ohio University, Camp was an instructor in General Botany, Local Flora, and Plant Anatomy until he left in 1936 to join the staff of the New York Botanical Garden as Assistant Curator, where he eventually advanced to Associate Curator in 1946. In 1949, Camp moved on to the Academy of Natural Sciences in Philadelphia where he took on the position of Curator of Experimental Botany and Horticulture and later became the Director of the Taylor Memorial Arboretum. While in New York and Philadelphia, Camp served on the graduate faculties of Columbia University and the University of Pennsylvania. In 1953, Camp came to the University of Connecticut as Department Head and Professor of Botany. At the University of Connecticut, Camp taught Introductory Botany and advanced courses in Floristics, Systematics, and Economic Botany. On February 4, 1963, Dr. Wendell H. Camp died at his home in Storrs, Connecticut, after a prolonged battle with cancer. A detailed biography and list of accomplishments is available here.
Scope and Content
The collection contains the correspondence, papers, essays, negatives and photographs associated with the research and instruction interests of Wendell H. Camp. Series II contains manuscript drafts and chapters of a book about his travels in Oaxaca, Mexico in the late 1930s.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged topically.
Series I: Biographical materials ( undated, 1929-1941 )
Series II: Correspondence and writings ( undated, circa 1937-1954 )
Series III: Photographic prints and negatives ( undated, circa 1937 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information about this collection please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Custodial History
The materials were found in a laboratory in the Torrey Life Sciences building (UConn, Storrs campus) in 2005.
Acquisition Information
This collection was transfered through a donation by Andrew Doran (Scientific Collections Manager, George S. Torrey Herbarium, Dept. of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology) in February 2006 to the University Archives.
Camp, Wendell Holmes, 1904-1963.; New York Botanical Garden; Taylor Memorial Arboretum; University of Connecticut.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Storrs (Conn.)
- Series I: Biographical materials, undated, 1929-1941
  - Bibliography, 1929-1941 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Biographical information (Box 1:, Folder 2)
- Series II: Correspondence and writings, undated, circa 1937-1954
  - Correspondence, 1950-1953 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Reh, Emma, 1938 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    General note
    [includes negative and print]
  - Notes, undated (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Notes, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - "Biosystematic Analysis as a tool for detecting migrants,", undated (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - "Continental Displacement,", 1947-1949 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - "Evolution in the Plant Kingdom,", 1933, 1954 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - "Modern Economic Plant--A Product of Biological Engineering,", undated (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - "Native Plant Garden,", undated (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - "NE Decid. Forest (Paper given in Montreal), 1947 August (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - "Plants and Man,", undated (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - "Population Studies in Stemless Blue Violets,", undated (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - "Problems with the correlation of the systematics of tertiary and modern flowering plants,", undated (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - "Sex,", 1931 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - "Soil micro organisms,", undated (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - " South America n geology," (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - "Synopsis of the orders and families of flowering plants,", undated (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - "To a scorpion,", undated (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - Untitled [manuscript of book], circa 1937
    - Foreword (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - The Valley where the Huaxin Grows (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - The Land of the Cloud People (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - House in Oaxaca (Box 1:, Folder 24)
    - El Rio Zavaleta [darft] (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - El Rio Zavaleta (Box 1:, Folder 26)
    - The Place of Twenty Peaks [draft with photographs] (Box 2:, Folder 27)
    - The Place of Twenty Peaks (Box 2:, Folder 28)
    - There was a hint of moisture in the air (Box 2:, Folder 29)
    - And so the Days pass (Box 2:, Folder 30)
    - Candles for the Virgin (Box 2:, Folder 31)
    - Market (Box 2:, Folder 32)
    - Pepe (Box 2:, Folder 33)
    - This day our daily bread (Box 2:, Folder 34)
    - Twilight of the gods (Box 2:, Folder 35)
    - We have a mountain to climb (Box 2:, Folder 36)
  - Unsorted materials, 1933-1954 (Box 4)
    Scope and Content Note
    [Subjects include: Manuscripts, Notes, Correspondence, Transcripts, Books on Botany, Systematic Biology.]
- Series III: Photographic prints and negatives, undated, circa 1937
  - Photographic prints (B&W) and associated negatives (approx. 150), undated, circa 1937 (Box 3)